<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Data Analytics on LIN Tzu Chun (Ryan)</title>
    <link>https://theryanlin.github.io/tags/data-analytics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Data Analytics on LIN Tzu Chun (Ryan)</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://theryanlin.github.io/tags/data-analytics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>K-means: Quickly Review Data in Datathon</title>
      <link>https://theryanlin.github.io/posts/2020/09/13/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theryanlin.github.io/posts/2020/09/13/</guid>
      <description>K-means clustering is a widely used and easy-applied algorithm! In this article, I would quickly review clustering methods and show how I used this during the Datathon.
Clustering Clustering is the most common task in a real-life situation, for example, an e-commerce company usually divides customers into different groups and give them customized campaigns. Also, a factory group the same functional machines to be back up in order to maintain the high yield-rate when one machine is broken.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sportportal: People Numbers Prediction in 2020 Datathon</title>
      <link>https://theryanlin.github.io/posts/2020/09/12/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://theryanlin.github.io/posts/2020/09/12/</guid>
      <description>I always grab any chance to get hands-on experience also try to solve a real problem. Recently, my 2 ex-colleagues at Gogoro with me joined in 2020 Datathon, like a workshop. I am writing to share my steps and the solution!
Before Coding In the beginning, we don&amp;rsquo;t limit our thoughts on data the host provides, then we come up with so many ideas. That&amp;rsquo;s to say, the host provides invoice data, weather data, and internet posts, therefore people no doubt do analysis on the relationship between weather and consumption habits.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>